<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<page>
<title>Roadmap</title>

<description>
Plan for the introduction of new features in future versions.
</description>

<keywords>nice, roadmap, features
</keywords>

<para>
This is the current plan for future versions of the language.
Comments about the new features are welcome. 
This includes arguing whether they are well designed, proposing alternatives,
requesting that some feature should be given a higher priority because
you need them more and proposing new features.
Each feature should have a link, which leads to a Wiki page where
it is possible to discuss its design and its implementation.
</para>

<para>
You can see the features that have been implemented recently by looking
at the 
<ulink
url="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/nice/Nice/NEWS?rev=HEAD">
news file</ulink>. These features are available when using the
<ulink url="install.html">
latest released version of the compiler</ulink>, or for most recent ones, 
by installing the
<ulink
url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/DevelopmentVersion">
latest development version</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>1.0</term>
<listitem>
<para>

Improve the <ulink 
url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/NiceConstructors">
support for object creation</ulink>, besides automatic constructors.

Add <ulink
url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/EnumImplementation">
enumerations</ulink> to the language.

Implement <ulink 
url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/VisibilityModifiers">
visibility modifiers</ulink> (private, default, public).

<ulink url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/StandardLibrary">
Improve and document the standard library <literal>nice.lang</literal></ulink>.

</para>
<para>
A <ulink
url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/EclipsePlugin">
plugin</ulink> to write Nice programs in <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org">
Eclipse</ulink> will also be included.

Finish a first version of the <ulink url="manual.html">User's manual</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
This will be the first official stable release of the language. 
This will be the time for
<ulink url="http://nice.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/twiki/view/Dev/AnnouncingNewReleases">
more widespread publicity</ulink>, to which everyone is welcome to contribute.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>0.8 (released on May 29th, 2003)</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Added various missing Java constructs: super, synchronized statements,
Java 1.4 style assertions, and Java 1.5-compatible generic classes.
Also implemented Design By Contract features: pre- and post-conditions for 
methods.
Method dispatch can be done on boolean and integer values.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

</page>
